





Postdoc Researcher

BIO

I am a Uruguayan biologist (PhD) doing research in Macroecology and Biodiversity Informatics. Currently, I am a postdoc researcher at the Czech University of Life Sciences (MOBI Lab), focused on studying of spatial and temporal patterns of biodiversity. I am also the founder of Biodiversidata (Uruguayan Consortium of Biodiversity Data), a member of the JULANA NGO, the administrator of NaturalistaUY (the iNaturalist site for Uruguay), and a NatGeoExplorer. I co-chair the RDA Sharing Rewards and Credit Interest Group (SHARC) and I am a GBIF Open Data Ambassador.

EDUCATION

2017 - 2021	Ph.D., Life Sciences University of Lincoln, United Kingdom Evolution and Ecology Research Group, School of Life Sciences. Dissertation: Biodiversity in- formatics and macroecological patterns of biodiversity: Uruguay as a model region. Advisor: Daniel Pincheira-Donoso
2013 - 2015	M.Sc., Biological Sciences (Genetics) Universidad de la República, Uruguay Department of Biodiversity and Genetics, Clemente Estable Biological Research Institute. Dissertation: Contributions of molecular ecology to the study of mammals in Uruguay. Advisors: Susana González and Mariana Cosse
2006 – 2012	B.Sc. (Hons), Biological Sciences Universidad de la República, Uruguay Department of Biodiversity and Genetics, Clemente Estable Biological Research Institute. Project: Development of molecular tools for the taxonomic identification of different carnivore species. Advisor: Mariana Cosse

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

PROFESSIONAL EXPE	MENCE	
04/2021 - present	Postdoc Czech University of Life Sciences (Czech Republic) Range dynamics of Neotropical carnivores in the MOBI Lab, Department of Spatial Sciences.	
01/2021 - 04/2021	Intern UN Environmental Programme - World Conservation Monitoring Centre (Cambridge, UK) Knowledge Management internship in the Conserving Land and Seascapes Team	
08/2018 - 12/2020 part time	Demonstrator University of Lincoln (Lincoln, United Kingdom) Demonstrating for courses of Zoology, Paleontology, and Biological Anthropology at the School of Life Sciences	
01/2017 - 07/2017 part time	Project Manager Co-coordination of the project 'Conservation in private protected areas of Uruguay'	
11/2016 - 03/2017	Research Assistant Universidad de la República (Montevideo, Uruguay) Bioinformatics and genomics at the Department of Animal Genetics, School of Veterinary	
10/2016 - 11/2016	Field Assistant Sampling plots of vascular plants for the project 'Rural Futures' Technische Universität Berlin (Uruguay)	
11/2015 - 10/2016 part time	Technician Livestock pedigree data management Rural Association of Uruguay (Montevideo, Uruguay)	
11/2015 - 10/2016 part time	Research Assistant Universidad de la República (Montevideo, Uruguay) Bioinformatics and comparative genomics of Salmonella at the Institute of Hygiene, School of Medicine	
01/2012 - 12/2015	Research Assistant Clemente Estable Biological Research Institute (Montevideo, Uruguay) Research and teaching at the Department of Biodiversity and Genetics	
05/2012 - 04/2014 part time	Teaching Assistant Universidad de la República (Montevideo, Uruguay) Organization of outreach ativities at the Extension Unit, School of Science	

PEER-REVIEWED ARTICLES

- 12. Pincheira-Donoso D., Harvey L.P., <u>Grattarola F.</u>, Winter M., Jara M., Cotter S.C., Tregenza T. & Hodgson D.J. (2021) The multiple origins of sexual size dimorphism in global amphibians. *Global Ecology and Biogeography*, 30(2): 443-458. [link]
- 11. <u>Grattarola F.</u>, Martínez-Lanfranco, J.A., ... & Pincheira-Donoso D. (2020) Multiple forms of hotspots of tetrapod biodiversity and the challenges of open-access data scarcity. *Scientific Reports*, 10(1): 1-15. [link]
- 10. <u>Grattarola F.</u>, Mai, P., ... & Pincheira-Donoso D. (2020) Biodiversidata: A novel dataset for the vascular plant species diversity in Uruguay. *Biodiversity Data Journal*, 8: e56850. [link]
- 9. <u>Grattarola F.</u> & Rodríguez-Tricot L. (2020) Mammals of Paso Centurión, an area with relicts of Atlantic Forest in Uruguay. *Neotropical Biology and Conservation*, 15(3): 267–283. [link]
- 8. D'Alessandro B., Pérez Escanda V., Balestrazzi V., <u>Grattarola F.</u>, ... & Betancor L. (2020) Comparative genomics of Salmonella enterica serovar Enteritidis ST-11 isolated in Uruguay reveals lineages associated with particular epidemiological traits. *Scientific Reports*, 10: 3638. [link]
- 7. <u>Grattarola F.</u>, Botto, G., ... & Pincheira-Donoso D. (2019) Biodiversidata: an open-access biodiversity database for Uruguay. *Biodiversity Data Journal*, 7: e36226. [link]
- 6. <u>Grattarola F.</u> & Pincheira-Donoso D. (2019) Data-sharing in Uruguay, the vision of collectors and data users. **Boletín de la Sociedad Zoológica del Uruguay**, 28(1): 1-14. [link]
- 5. Bergós L., <u>Grattarola F.</u>, Barreneche J.M., Herández D., & González S. (2018) Fogones de Fauna: an experience of participatory monitoring of wildlife in rural Uruguay. *Society & Animals*, 26(2), 171-185. [link]
- 4. Chouhy M., Santos C., Gaucher L., <u>Grattarola F.,</u> ... & Perazza, G. (2017) At the frontiers of knowledge: the quest for an integral training course on society-nature. *Integralidad Sobre Ruedas*, 4(1): 62–77. [link]
- 3. Cosse M., <u>Grattarola F.</u> & Mannise N. (2017) A novel real-time TaqMan[™]PCR assay for simultaneous detection of Neotropical fox species using noninvasive samples based on cytochrome C oxidase subunit II. *Mammal Research*, 62(4): 405-411. [link]
- 2. <u>Grattarola F.</u>, Hernández D., ... & Rodríguez-Tricot R. (2016) First record of jaguarundi (Puma yagouaroundi) (Mammalia: Carnivora: Felidae) in Uruguay, with comments about participatory monitoring. *Boletín de la Sociedad Zoológica del Uruguay*, 25(1): 85-91. [link]
- 1. <u>Grattarola F.</u>, Cosse M. & González S. (2015) A novel primer set for mammal species identification from feces samples. *Conservation Genetic Resources*, 7: 57–59. [link]

PRE-PRINT ARTICLES

- 2. <u>Grattarola F.</u>, Bowler E.D. & Keil P. (2022) Integrating presence-only and presence-absence data to model changes in species geographic ranges: An example of yaguarundi in Latin America. *EcoEvoRxiv*. [link]
- 1. Pincheira-Donoso D., Harvey L.P., Guirguis J., Goodyear L.E.B., Finn C., Johnson J.V., <u>Grattarola F.</u> (2022) Temporal and spatial patterns of vertebrate extinctions during the Anthropocene. *bioRxiv*. [link]

BOOKS

1. Chouhy M., Bergós L., Garay A., <u>Grattarola F.</u>, Perazza G., Santos C. & Taks J. (2022) Relaciones Sociedad-Naturaleza en Paso Centurión. Aportes desde una trayectoria integral universitaria en la frontera noreste de Uruguay. *Servicio Central de Extensión y Actividades en el Medio Universidad de la República*. [link]

GRANTS, FUNDING

2022	Capacity Enhancement Support Programme G £14,000 Project 'Extending knowledge on biodiversity of Spanish-speaking community' CESP2021-007 [link]	Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF) / data quality and publication in the	
2021 - 2022	Citizen Science for Species Discovery Grant £25,000 Project 'Naturalista UY – The iNaturalist commun	National Geographic Society nity for Uruguay' (Uruguay)	
2019	College of Science Grant for Postgraduate Students £750 Attend the conference 'Biodiversity Next' (Leiden, Th	University of Lincoln ne Netherlands)	

2019	Travel Grant for Postgraduate Students £500 Attend the course 'Advancing in statistical modelling for evolutionary biologists and ecologists using R' (Glasgow, Scotland)	
2018	Mobility Fund for Postgraduate Research StudentsSantander - University of Lincoln£500 Deliver the 'First meeting of the members of Biodiversidata' (Montevideo, Uruguay)	
2018	Travel Grant for Early Career European Researchers & Scientists £1,500 Attend the '11th RDA Plenary Meeting' (Berlin, Germany)	
2017 - 2020	Ph.D. International Fellowship September 1, 2016 1, 2016 1, 2016 2,	
2017	Travel Grant for Postgraduate Students Centro Brasileiro-Argentino de Biotecnologia (CBAB/CABBIO) £1,800 Attend the Course 'Bioinformatics Tools for RNA-Sequence Data Analysis' at Laboratório Nacional de Computação Científica (Petrópolis, RJ, Brasil)	
2015	Internship Grant for Postgraduate Students Association of Universities of the Montevideo Group (AUGM) £1,500 Internship stay at the Laboratório de Biodados, Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais (UFMG) (Belo Horizonte, Brazil)	
2013	Internship Grant for Postgraduate Students Program for the Development of Basic Sciences (PEDECIBA) £1,500 Internship stay at Bioinformatics at the Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, University of Mississippi (Starkville, United States)	
2013 – 2015	Posgraduate National Fellowship National Agency for Research and Innovation (ANII) £8,500 Postgraduate Fellowship POS_NAC_2012_1_8976 (Montevideo, Uruguay)	
2012	Travel Grant £1,500 Attend the 'VIII Genetic Workshop for Conservation: new tools and new concepts' (Chillán, Chile)	
2012	Mobility Grant Association of Universities of the Montevideo Group (AUGM) £2,000 A semester at Universidade Estadual de Jaboticabal (UNESP) (Jaboticabal, SP, Brazil)	
2011 - 2012	Posgraduate National Fellowship National Agency for Research and Innovation (ANII) £2,000 Initiation in Research Fellowship BE_INI_2010_1961 (Montevideo, Uruguay)	

STUDENTS

Enzo Cavalli, BSc (Honours) in Biological Sciences, School of Science, **Universidad de la República**. Project: 'Effects of livestock on the mammal community of Paso Centurión, Cerro Largo'. Advisor, finished in 2019. [thesis]

Rodrigo Montiel, BSc (Honours) in Biological Sciences, School of Science, **Universidad de la República**. Project: 'NaturalistaUY as a community science tool to improve biodiversity knowledge in Uruguay'. Advisor, ongoing.

LECTURING

2022	Spatial Ecology and Macroecology Practical classes in the posgraduate course for 6-8 students. Taught together with François Leroy and led by Dr. Petr Keil [syllabus]
2017 – 2019 two editions	Modern Mammals School of Science, Universidad de la República (Uruguay) Lecture in the graduate course of Palaeontology, for 15-20 students. Invited by Dr. Richard Fariña [slides]
2018	Management and analysis of camera trap records using R Ministry of Environment (Uruguay) Course for NGOs, researchers and government people. Taught together with Juan M. Barreneche and Gabriel Perazza [syllabus]
2016 – 2017 two editions	Introduction to Python Universidad de la República, Uruguay Lecture at posgraduate course 'Introduction to command line and programming for bioinformatic analysis', for 25-30 students in Biological Sciences. Invited by Dr. Andrís Iriarte [syllabus]
2013 – 2017 four editions	Relationships between Society and Nature Graduate course for 10-20 students of Anthropology, Biology, Geography and Social Sciences. Taught together with Carlos Santos, Javier Taks, Magdalena Chouhy, Andrea Garay, Lucía

Bergós and Gabriel Perazza [link to S&N Group]

2014 **Environmental education and community involvement** Universidad de la República, Uruguay

Lecture at posgraduate course 'Conservation biology' for 15-20 students in Biological Sciences.

Invited by Dr. Susana González.

2014 Introduction to Biology Universidad de la República, Uruguay

Discussion group for the course Introduction to Biology School or 15-20 undergraduate stu-

dents of Biological Sciences. Taught together with Dr. Juan Cristina.

SERVICE FOR JOURNALS ACADEMIC MEMBERSHIPS

Frontiers of Biogeography 2021 - International Biogeography Society. Biodiversity Data Journal. 2020 - GBIF Biodiversity Open Data Ambassador.

Global Ecology and Biogeography 2019 - Organization for Women in Science for the Developing World (OWSD).

Journal of Biogeography 2018 - British Ecological Society (BES).

2018 - Research Data Alliance (RDA) - SHARC Interest Group. 2018 - Uruguayan Consortium of Biodiversity Data (Biodiversidata). CITATION METRICS

2013 – Interdisciplinary Group on Society-Nature Relationships (RETEMA).

2012 – Latin American Network for Conservation Genetics (REGENEC).

2010 - Zoological Society of Uruguay (SZU).

TRAINING

2022 Joint Species Distribution Modelling with Hierarchical Modelling of Species Communities Jyväskylä, Finland Jyväskylä University

2022 Research Data Science Summer School Trieste, Italy

CODATA-RDA

2020 Using Python to Access Web Data Virtual

Coursera

Google Scholar (06/2022)

77 citations, h-index = 5

2019 Species Distribution Modelling: Fundamentals and the Future Nottingham, UK

University of Nottingham, British Ecological Society

2019 Advancing in statistical modelling for evolutionary biologists and ecologists using R Glasgow, Scotland

PR Statistics

2017 Bioinformatics Tools for RNA-Sequence Data Analysis Petrópolis, Brazil

Laboratório Nacional de Computação Científica

2017 From Complex Networks to Social Networks: Introduction to the Use of Big Data Montevideo, Uruguay

Espacio Interdisciplinario, Universidad de la República

2016 WGCAC Human and Vertebrate Genomics: Bioinformatics Tools and Resources Montevideo, Uruguay

Wellcome Trust, UK

2015 Next Generation Sequencing Strtegies Belo Horizonte, Brazil

Universidad Federal de Minas Gerais

TALKS

2022 Open data, community science and environmental education in Uruguay

Grattarola F.* / I Encuentro Internacional sobre Educación Abierta Ambiental: enseñanza, activismo e investigación [slides]

Online

2022 How Open Science activities are perceived and recognised in Research and the Research career Seoul, Korea Grattarola F.*, Shmagun H., Mabile L. & Cambon-Thomsen A. / International Data Week 2022 - RDA Plenary Breakout [conference]

2021 As a naturalist in my country, where are there more opportunities to fill in information gaps? Online

<u>Grattarola F.</u>* & Barreneche J.M. / LatinR Conference [code repo] 2021 Roundtable: Activism through digital media Montevideo, Uruguay

Grattarola F.* / 4th Conference on Digital Citizenship [video]

2021	The value of open education policies to promote environmental education <u>Grattarola F.*</u> / CILAC Latin American Open Science Forum [video]	Online	
2020 Invited	Hotspots of biodiversity and the challenges of open-data scarcity Grattarola F.* / Seminar of the Department of Spatial Sciences, Czech University of Life Sciences Prague		
2019	Biodiversity hotspots in Uruguay: real or fabricated? <u>Grattarola F.* & D. Pincheira-Donoso / British Ecological Society Annual Meeting [slides]</u>	Belfast, Northern Ireland	
2019	Biodiversidata: a collaborative initiative towards open data availability in Uruguay Grattarola F.* & D. Pincheira-Donoso / Biodiversity Next Conference [abstract]	Leiden, The Netherlands	
2019 Invited		Leiden, The Netherlands	
2019 Invited	Biodiversity hotspots in Uruguay Grattarola F.* & D. Pincheira-Donoso / School of Life Sciences Postgraduate Symposium, U.	Lincoln, United Kingdom Iniversity of Lincoln	
2019	iNaturalist as a tool to enhance the conservation of biodiversity in Uruguay Grattarola F.* / Rufford Conference Uruguay [video]	donado, Uruguay (online)	
2017	Landscape genetics of the crab-eating fox Cerdocyon thous (Carnivora: Canidae) <u>Grattarola F.*</u> , Bartesaghi L., Hernández D., Soutullo A., Mannise N., González S. & Cosse M. ology Congress	Montevideo, Uruguay / IV Uruguayan Zo-	
2016	Humans and fauna in Paso Centurión (Cerro Largo) from an interdisciplinary perspective Chouhy M.*, Garay A., Bergós L.,Gaucher L., Perazza G., <u>Grattarola F.</u> & Santos C. / III Interdiscon Biodiversity and Ecology		
2016	Democratization of information in the context of territorial management Gaucher L.*, Hernández D., <u>Grattarola F.</u> , Rodriguez-Tricot L., Duarte A., Perazza G. & Gonzále plinary Conference on Biodiversity and Ecology	Montevideo, Uruguay ez, S / III Interdisci-	
2016	Molecular detection of species and sex determination in road killed foxes in Uruguay Mannise N.*, Cosse M., <u>Grattarola F.</u> , Repetto L. & González S. / First Ibero-American Congand Road Infrastructure	Lavras, Brazil ress on Biodiversity	
SCI C	сомм		
2022	Workshop in preparation for the Greatern Southern Bioblitz 2020 in NaturalistaUY Live talk streamed on YouTube for NaturalistaUY users [video]		
2022	Community science outreach with JULANA and NaturalistaUY Radio interview by Diego Varela and Fernanda Cabrera for Radio Fénix [video]		
2022	Scientific Pokemon Go Podcast episode by Soledad Machado for Medios Públicos [episode]		
2020	Biodiversidata began to digitize the herbarium of the National Museum of Natural History Press note by Leo Lagos for La Diaria [article]		
2021	iNaturalist - What is it and what can it do for our project? Talk with students of the Polo Educativo Tecnológico Arrayanes (Park Rangers) [slides]		
2020	Getting started with iNaturalist - Project RACATÚ Online talk with primary school students from rural school N102 of Berachi (Cerro Largo, Uruguay) [slides]		
2020	Uruguayans are wanted to participate in a platform that helps scientists Press note by Analía Filosi for Diario El País [article]		
2019	iNaturalist: a bet on citizen science Talk at Museum of Natural History Torres de la Llosa [slides]		
2019	iNaturalist a citizen science tool to improve biodiversity knowledge in Uruguay Radio interview by Juan Vique in Radio Uruguay [radiocut]		

 ${\tt 2019} \quad \textbf{The Uruguayan Consortium of Biodiversity Data, Biodiversidata, published the first open data set} \\$

Press note by Leo Lagos for La Diaria [article]

2019 Series 'Gender and IT' - Pan Ceibal

Online talk with students from Canelones, Paysandú, Tacuarembó and Treinta y Tres' primary schools in Uruguay

2019 Biodiversidata: Biodiversity Open Data

Online talk at the Third Edition of 'Datos y Cogollos: Open Data in Uruguay'. La Diaria Media Lab (Montevideo, Uruguay)

2019 Exhibition 'A Computer of One's Own'

Art exhibition about pioneer women in Computer Science at CSSconf and JSConf (Berlin, Germany) [project]

2018 Big data in biodiversity

Radio interview with Federico Weinstein in the science segment of the program Justicia Infinita, Radio Océano (93.9 FM) (Montevideo, Uruguay)

2017 The Marsh Seedeater

Video production for PROBIDES organization [video]

2016 Drawn news: First record of a jaguarundi in Uruguay

Video production for JULANA NGO [video]